The talented young herbalist named Xu Xian
was in trouble.
It should have been a victorious /vɪkˈtɔːriəs 胜利的/ moment–
he had just opened his very
own medicine shop.
But he bought his supplies from
his former employer,
and the resentful /rɪˈzɛntfʊl 怨恨的/ man
sold him rotten /ˈrɒtən 腐烂de/ herbs.
As Xu Xian wondered what to do with this
useless inventory /ˈɪnvəntərɪ 存货/,
patients flooded into his shop.
A plague /pleɪɡ 瘟疫/ had stricken /ˈstrɪkən 侵袭/ the city,
and he had nothing to treat them.
Just as he was starting to panic /ˈpænɪk 惊慌/,
his wife, Bai Su Zhen, produced a recipe /ˈrɛsɪpɪ 处方/
to use the rotten /ˈrɒtən 腐烂de/ herbs as medicine.
Her remedy /ˈrɛmɪdɪ 治疗/ cured all the plague-afflicted /əˈflɪkt 折磨/
citizens immediately.
Xu Xian’s former boss even had to buy back
some of the rotten herbs
to treat his own family.
Shortly after, a monk /mʌŋk/ named Fa Hai
approached Xu Xian,
warning him that there was
a demon /ˈdiːmən/ in his house.
The demon, he said, was Bai Su Zhen.
Xu Xian laughed.
His kindhearted, resourceful /机智/ wife
was not a demon.
Fa Hai insisted.
He told Xu Xian to serve his wife realgar /rɪˈælɡə 雄黄 /
wine /swine 猪/ on the 5th day of the 5th month,
when demons’ powers are weakest.
If she wasn’t a demon, he explained,
it wouldn’t hurt her.
Xu Xian dismissed the monk politely /pəˈlaɪtlɪ/,
with no intention /ɪnˈtɛnʃən 意图/ of serving
Bai Su Zhen the wine.
But as the day approached,
he decided to try it.
As soon as the wine touched
Bai Su Zhen’s lips,
she ran to the bedroom,
claiming she wasn’t feeling well.
Xu Xian prepared some medicine
and went to check on her.
But instead /ɪnˈstɛd/ of his wife,
he found a giant white serpent /ˈsɜːpənt  蛇/ with a
bloody forked tongue /tʌŋ  舌头/ in the bed.
He collapsed /kəˈlæps 衰竭/, killed by the shock /ʃɒk/.
When Bai Su Zhen opened her eyes,
she realized immediately what
must have happened.
The truth was that Bai Su Zhen was
an immortal /ɪˈmɔːtəl 不朽的/ snake
with formidable /fɔːˈmɪdəbəl 难对付的/ magical powers.
She had used her powers to take a
human form
and improve her and
her husband’s fortunes.
Her magic couldn’t revive /rɪˈvaɪv 复活/ Xu Xian,
but she had one more idea to save him:
an herb that could grant /grænt/ longevity /lɒnˈdʒɛvɪtɪ 长寿/
and even bring the dead back to life,
guarded /ˈɡɑːdɪd 被监督的/ by the Old Man of the South Pole /pəʊl/
in the forbidden peaks of the
Kun Lun Mountains.
She rode /ride过去/ to the mountains on a cloud,
then continued on foot passed gateways
and arches /ɑːtʃ 拱门/
until she reached one
marked “beyond mortals /ˈmɔːtəl 凡人/”
hanging over a silver bridge.
On the other side,
two of the Old Man’s disciples /dɪˈsaɪpəl 门徒/
guarded the herb.
Bai Su Zhen disguised /dɪsˈɡaɪz 伪装/ herself as a monk
and told them she’d come to invite
the Old Man to a gathering of the gods.
While they relayed /ˈriːleɪ 传达/ her message,
she plucked /plʌk 采/ some leaves
from the herb and ran.
The servants /ˈsɜːvənt 仆人/ realized they had been
tricked and chased her.
Bai Su Zhen coughed /kɒf 咳嗽/ up a magic ball
and threw it at one.
As the other closed in on her,
she put the herb under her tongue
for safekeeping,
but its magic forced both of them
into their true forms.
As the crane’/kreɪn 鹤/s long beak /biːk 鸟喙/
clamped / klæmp 夹紧/ around her,
the Old Man appeared.
Why, he asked, would she risk her life
to steal his herb
when she was already immortal?
Bai Su Zhen explained
her love for Xu Xian.
Even if he didn’t want to be with her
now that he knew she was a demon,
she was determined to
bring him back to life.
The two had a karmic /ˈkɑːmɪk 宿命/ connection dating
back more than a thousand years.
When Bai Su Zhen was a small snake,
a beggar /ˈbɛɡə 乞丐/ was about to kill her,
but a kind passerby rescued her.
Her rescuer was Xu Xian in a past life.
Touched by her willingness
to risk her life for him,
the Old Man permitted her to leave the
mountain with the immortal herb.
Bai Su Zhen returned home
to revive Xu Xian.
When he opened his eyes,
the terrified look frozen on his face
became a smile.
Demon or not,
he was still happy to see his wife.